William Marion Jardine Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
William Marion Jardine Papers 1908-1955
MSS27698
Jardine, William Marion, 1879-1955
920 items
8 containers plus 2 oversize
3.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Educator, public official, and diplomat. Correspondence, articles, speeches, lectures, notes, and scrapbooks of clippings concerned mainly with the economic aspects of agriculture and rural life. The greatest concentration, 1925-1929, relates to Jardine's term as secretary of agriculture. Other papers cover the four years during which he was minister to Egypt. Additional files concern his tenure as president of the University of Wichita, 1934-1949.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Eisenhower, Milton Stover, 1899-1985--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Jardine, William Marion, 1879-1955.; Landon, Alfred M. (Alfred Mossman), 1887-1987--Correspondence.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1937--Correspondence.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950--Correspondence.; Woodring, Harry Hines, 1887-1967--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Department of Agriculture.; University of Wichita.
Subjects
Agriculture--Economic aspects.; Diplomatic and consular service, American--Egypt.; Rural conditions.
Places
Egypt--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Egypt.
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Diplomats.; Educators.; Public officials.
Provenance
The papers of William Marion Jardine, educator, public official, and diplomat, were given to the Library of Congress in 1955 by his wife, Effie Nebeker Jardine.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of William Marion Jardine are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1879, Jan. 16 Born, Oneida County, Idaho
1904 B.S., Agricultural College of Utah, Logan, Utah
1905 Instructor, Agricultural College of Utah, Logan, Utah
1905, Sept. 6 Married Effie Nebeker
1905 1906 Professor, Agricultural College of Utah, Logan, Utah
1907 1910 Assistant United States cerealist in charge of dry land grain investigations
1912 Lecturer, Graduate School of Agriculture, Michigan Agricultural College, East Lansing, Mich.
1913 1918 Director of Experiment Station and Dean of Agriculture, Kansas State Agricultural College, Manhattan, Kans.
1918 1925 President, Kansas State Agricultural College, Manhattan, Kans.
1925 1929 Secretary of agriculture
1930 1933 Envoy extraordinary and minister plenipotentiary to Egypt
1933 1934 State treasurer of Kansas
1934 1949 President, University of Wichita, Wichita, Kansas
1949 1955 President Emeritus, University of Wichita, Wichita, Kansas
1955, Jan. 17 Died, San Antonio, Tex.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of William Marion Jardine (1879-1955) span the years 1908-1955 and consist of correspondence, articles, speeches, lectures, notes, and scrapbooks of clippings relating chiefly to his career as secretary of agriculture, minister to Egypt, and president of the University of Wichita. The greatest concentration of material consits of four volumes of congratulatory messages dated 1925 and a substantial amount of material for the 1929-1933 period. The scrapbooks are most complete for the years 1925-1929. The correspondence relates to politics, economic problems, and especially with various aspects of agriculture. The majority of Jardine's speeches and articles concern agricultural topics. Among the correspondents are Milton Stover Eisenhower, Herbert Hoover, Alfred M. Landon, Andrew W. Mellon, Henry L. Stimson, and Harry Hines Woodring.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material and therein chronologically.
Container List
- Articles, 1908-1922, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1)
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Congratulatory, 1925, (2 folders) (Box 1, Box 2)
  - General (Box 2)
    - 1924-1929, (3 folders) (Box 2)
    - 1930-1941, (10 folders) (Box 3)
    - 1942-1955, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
- Extracts of speeches, reports, and writings, 1926-1928 (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks (Box 4)
  - 1918-1923 (Box 4)
  - 1924-1925, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - 1925, (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - 1925-1943 See also Oversize, (4 folders) (Box 7)
  - 1949 (Box 8)
- Speeches, 1908-1944, undated, (4 folders) (Box 8)
- Oversize (Box OV1)
  - Scrapbooks (Box OV1)
    - 1927-1929, (Container 7) (Box OV1)
    - 1927-1929, (Container 7) (Box OV2)